# 大家好 今天去看一下兄弟跟攝影小哥一起種的那個
Hi everyone! Today we're gonna take a look at the, the shi hu planted by Mr. Cameraman,
# 鐵皮石斛啊
and our buddy.
# 看一下還在不在
Let's see if they're still there.
# 前幾年前種的哦 就在那前面
They were planted a couple of years go. There, right in front of us.
# 哇 這路都那麼靚啦
Wa! Why is this path so beautiful now?
# 你看 這大片都是哦
Look! It's the whole area here.
# 棚子都爛啦 沒有管 裡面都是好多草啦
The sheds have already run-down. No one takes care of them anymore and they're now full of weed.
# 當初他們投了 好像應該有幾十萬吧
At that time, they have invested something like hundreds of thousands RMB.
# 就成這樣子啦
And that's how it looks now.
# 太浪費啦
What a waste!
# 到時候我看一下我家裡有沒有地方
Let me see if I can spare some spaces at my place.
# 在我家田里面搞幾個棚子起來
Then I can build a couple of sheds on my field.
# 把它們全部撿回去 反正他們不要啦
I'll take them all back home. They've given them up anyway.
# 我來撿回去
Let me take them back.
# 萬一漲價了呢
Who knows? The price may go up.
# 就在這裡面 我進去看一下
It's right inside. Let me get in and have a look.
# 哇 全是雜草叢生
Wa! There's nothing but weed!
# 這個就是鐵皮石斛哦 現在們他沒有管理好
These are the shi hu. But now, they're not taking care of them anymore.
# 他們太忙了
They might be too busy.
# 所以就搞成這
So it's now,
# 造成這樣子 葉子都不見啦
it's now a big piece of mass. I can't even see any leaves.
# 這個原本要分支的
In fact these need to be branched.
# 他們就分都沒分 就這樣
But they didn't do anything at all.
# 也沒有人管 雜草叢生
Nobody takes care of it. There's nothing but weed.
# 看一下 嘖嘖 那麼漂亮的東西都被他們
Look! My god! It's so pretty but they've,
# 被他們 這樣糟糟蹋了
they've simply ruined it.
# 你看 這個都是可以吃的這個
Look! This is edible, you know.
# 就直接可以咬
You can chew it right away.
# 我來這樣 就這樣吃都可以吃
I can, like, eat it right here.
# 就是老 有點老
It's old, a bit old.
# 不嫩
Not tender at all.
# 這個是很漂亮的哦 這種
This is really, you know.
# 葉子都沒有啦
All leaves are gone.
# 我拿點回去煲湯
Let me take some to make a stew.
# 來都來了 哪有空手回去的道理
I'm already here. Getting back empty-handed is never an option.
# 這個
I think,
# 應該太遠啦 在這裡不好管理
it's way too far. Managing this place takes too much effort.
# 下次
Let me.
# 下次我在家也搞個這個棚
Let me also make such a shed at home.
# 搞這個棚 在這裡拔點苗回去
Make a shed, then I can bring some seedlings from here,
# 拔點苗回去種
bring some seedlings back from here.
# 反正
Well,
# 反正他們也不怎麼管
they've almost abandoned this place.
# 這種很值錢的哦 以前很值錢的 現在我就不知道
The price is really good. At least it used to be good. But I have no ideas now.
# 我記得前幾年的時候都
A couple of years go, it was like,
# 幾百快錢一斤啊 這個
hundreds to a thousand RMB a kilogram.
# 光這樣的 就這樣纖條
You see, they're just like a bunch of fibre.
# 就這樣 都幾百塊錢一斤
Nothing special. But it costs hundreds of RMB one kilogram.
# 你說值不值錢
Isn't it a good price?
# 比竹鼠還值錢
It costs even more than bamboo rats.
# 現在可能價格 價格下跌了一點
Now the price, the price might have come down a bit.
# 他們就不管啦
That's why they stopped growing it.
# 這樣怎麼行呢 是吧
How can it be? Isn't it?
# 我在家我也想搞個大棚來
I'm thinking of making a big shed at home.
# 把它拉回去
Let me take it back.
# 拉點回去 拉點回去種
Let me take some, take some and plant at home.
# 苗的話就在這裡拔 拔一點回去
The seedlings can be picked here. Let me pick some back home.
# 說不定萬一
Who knows? Just in case,
# 行情好了吶
if the sales are good,
# 那我不是賺大啦
then doesn't it mean that I can make a good fortune?
# 你看這種
Look! This is,
# 這種很靚的 這種
this is really beautiful, isn't it?
# 拿點回去
Let me pick some,
# 燉老母雞 剛好我家有個老母雞
to stew with an old hen. It just so happens that I have one at home.
# 這個葉子都自然掉啦
The leaves are coming off by themselves.
# 回家 回家拿去曬乾來
Take it back, take it back and dry it under the sun.
# 或者不用曬也行就直接扔下去
Or I don't even need to dry it. I can simply throw it into the pot,
# 燉雞湯
and stew with a hen,
# 或者燉排骨
or ribs.
# 這個很補的哦這個
It's really good for health you know.
# 這個 紅杏出牆 (註︰哇~!怎麼譯好呀)
This one, is looking for some affairs out here.
# 出到牆外面去我都把你抓回來
You're testing the limit but I'll get you back.
# 這個也可以做成盆景的哦
This one can also be used to make a bonsai,
# 這個很漂亮的
and is really beautiful.
# 不過現在沒種它
But I don't have any now.
# 我拔一棵 我拔一 幾棵 回去
Let me pick one, let me pick one, or some back home,
# 種 種成一個盆景 把它種 種好看一點
and make, make a bonsai, so that it looks better.
# 很漂亮的
It would be pretty.
# 種的不想種的時候就把它捏的來 像這樣子 捏的來
When I don't want it anymore, I can pick it out, like what I'm doing now, pick it out,
# 燉雞湯 嘖
and stew with chicken, wow!
# 一舉兩得
It's all up to me.
# 在家租一個這樣的棚子來種 把它全部 (註︰應該不是「租」，而做「造」)
I can make a similar shed at home, and then,
# 全部把它搬回去 它們不要啦
and then I can pick them all back. They don't want them anymore.
# 剛好帶了一個竹筒子過來
It just so happens that I have a bamboo bucket with me.
# 這個竹筒可以裝這個的哦
I can put the, you know, into the bucket.
# 你看 把這個塞滿
Look! Let me stuff it full.
# 種這個一定要用這個樹瞉
This kind of tree bark is a must if you wanna grow these things.
# 不然的話就不好種
It's not really possible otherwise.
# 不要那麼多
I don't need that much.
# 可以 誒詏 有刺啊
Alright! Yeeyo! Spikes!
# 你看 這裡有一棵
Look! Here's one!
# 這個樹瞉
The tree bark,
# 放多點這個樹瞉過去
let me stuff a bit more tree bark.
# 靚吧 你看
Isn't it beautiful? Look!
# 我把這個老的要把它捏掉 捏掉之後留下這個小的
I'm gonna pick away, the old ones need to be picked away, leaving only the small ones.
# 長出來就得漂亮 這個
Then it would be really pretty when it starts growing.
# 然後掛在這個
Then I can hang it on the,
# 柱 柱子上 你看
on the pill, pillar. Look!
# 這個還會開花的哦 這個花 它會不垂
There will even be flowers. The flowers will be, sagging,
# 它花會慢慢地下垂 垂下來
The flowers will be sagging, sagging down slowly.
# 垂那麼高 那麼長 嘖 這個
It will be that high, I mean that long, really.
# 好靚
Beautiful!
# 帶不盆回去 我帶盆回去
Let me take it back, take it back home,
# 放到自家陽台上
and place it onto my balcony.
# 等下種的它這
When it grows,
# 這個老的話就可以捏來 煲雞湯
The older parts can be picked, to stew with chickens,
# 煲 煲骨頭湯
or, or with bones.
# 好啦 回去啦
Alright! Let's go back.
# (第二天)
The next day
# 聽說兄弟養了一個很大的公雞哦
I've heard that my buddy has a really large rooster.
# 你看 那不是啊
Look! Isn't it that one?
# 就那個
Yeah, that one.
# 你看 它的那個雞冠都好紅啊 又大
Look! It has a really red, and big cockscomb.
# 你看
Look!
# 那個花的
That one is speckled.
# 它這公雞不會叫我哦
This rooster doesn't yelp at all.
# 我都沒聽它叫過
I've never heard it yelp.
# 理都不理我
No response.
# 肯定不會叫的 這公雞
I don't think it can help, this rooster.
# 不會叫的公雞就不是好公雞
A rooster is not a good rooster unless it yelps.
# 來
C'mon!
# 兄弟送了一個
My buddy just gave me a,
# 大公雞給我
a giant rooster.
# 有點毛 他沒幫我搞乾淨
There's still some hair. He didn't clean it well enough.
# 我把這個大腿缷下來
Let me chop off its leg.
# 不然它要翹起來這個腿
It would be kicking the lid otherwise.
# 就這樣 案板都不見啦 誒
I just do it here. The cutting board is gone again, ay!
# 這樣搞
Too bad.
# 前兩 前兩天用的那個案板就不見啦
I've, I've used it a couple of days ago. But now it's gone.
# 你看 裝點水 就直接這樣燜 (註︰他的煲呀，燉呀，炆呀，我不管了，反正他都是亂說的)
Look! I put some water, and then I can put it on the heat right away.
# 放到這個鍋子上來
Let me put it onto the stand.
# 把它們剁成三塊
I've cut them into three pieces.
# 把它放在這裡
Let me put it here.
# 誒 剛剛好 可以蓋得住
Eh? Perfect! It's just right!
# 我先把火升起來
Let me set the fire first.
# 誒呦喂
Yeyowei!
# 可以
Alright!
# 塞一點東西進去
Let me stuff something inside.
# 要不然
Otherwise,
# 不然火燒不著
otherwise it won't burn.
# 煙燻雞
Smoked chicken
# 你看這個(鐵皮)石斛 (註︰我不理會鐵皮了)
Have a look at the shi hu!
# 上次去兄弟家摘的
These were picked from my buddy's place.
# 洗一下 把它放下去
Let me wash it, and then put it in.
# 我把這個生薑跟那個(鐵皮)石斛放下去
I'll put in the ginger, together with the shi hu,
# 再加點鹽
and also some salt.
# 誒呀 香哦
Yeya! It smells great!
# 把這個(鐵皮)石斛放在這旁邊
I put the shi hu on the two side,
# 放在中間
and in the middle.
# 再把這個生薑
And then the ginger...
# 先中間 後兩邊
Middle first, followed by two sides
# 這個鹽要先放下去哦
The salt needs to be put first.
# 因為比較大一塊 大塊的那個 雞肉
Cuz the pieces are big, big pieces of, you know, chicken,
# 所以先放鹽它就 有助於
putting the salt first can enhance,
# 全身吸收
thorough absorption.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 再加點下去
Why not more?
# 夠啦
Enough
# 再加它蓋起來
Then cover it up.
# 看一下
Have a look
# 哇
Wa!
# 好香啊
It smells so good!
# 加點水 這水都快沒啦 要麼再煮一鍋水下去
More water, it's drying out. Shall I boil one more pot of water?
# 加點水
Refill some water.
# 看來它要找貪吃古玩去啦 (註︰「貪吃古」是苏洋對跃金的稱呼)
I think she's going to have some fun with Greedy Eater.
# 誒呀 來 這只棕色的小狗
Yeya! C'mon! This is a brown puppy.
# 它現在好瘦啊
She's now so skinny.
# 這母狗辛苦啦
This mother must have had a hard time.
# 你去旁邊玩吧
Go and enjoy yourself over there.
# 誒呀 好多狗啊
Yeeya! A lot of dogs
# 誒呀 這隻狗你還是這麼胖
Yeeya! This dog, you're still that chubby!
# 誒呀 這小 這小狗是蠻聽話的 別走
Yeeya! This pup, this puppy is rather nice. Don't run away!
# 這麼聽話的小狗 不要走 來
What a good puppy! Stay here! C'mon!
# 我幫你鬆鬆毛
Let me give you a massage.
# 你看現在熟了
Look! It's done now!
# 喂呀 這個雞腿
Weiya! This chicken leg...
# 看下 這個大一點
Let me see. This one is larger.
# 我吃這個
I'll take this one.
# 那麼大 太燙啦
It's giant! Too hot
# 哇 可以呦
Wa! It's not bad.
# 這個味道
I mean the taste.
# 嘿 走開 等下再吃
Hey! Go 'way! It's not yet your turn.
# 走燙
Really hot!
# 很有嚼勁 剛剛好
It's rather chewy. Perfect!
# 又不爛
And it's not too soft.
# 就是大了一點
It's just a little bit too big.
# 哇 很香啊 這個
Wa! It smells really good!
# 還有這個
And also this part,
# 也有點味道
It's quite flavourful too.
# 就額 這個 鉄皮石斛 也有一點這個味道
And eh, you know, the shi hu, is also quite flavourful.
# 就是鐵皮石斛的味道跟雞肉的味道 融洽在一起 (註︰想保留一個這個「融洽」的誤用)
It's like, the flavour of shi hu is harmonized with that of the chicken.
# 這個是大公雞來的哦
It's a giant rooster, you know.
# 這個皮心較有嚼勁的
So its skin is rather chewy.
# 不會像母雞一樣
It's very different from a hen's skin,
# 一燉就爛掉啦 這個不會
which gets too soft as soon as it's heated. But a rooster's don't.
# 它肉還較糯一點
Its meat is a bit mushy.
# 應該養了一年多的公雞 這個
I think this rooster is at least an year old.
# 嗯 這肉還蠻好吃的哦
Um! The meat is rather tasty.
# 這肉比較結實哦
The texture is rather firm, isn't it?
# 那麼大的腿
What an enormous leg!
# 要不要啊
Do you want some?
# 你看後面那條胖狗 口水都流出來了
Have a look at the big fat dog behind you. He's already drooling.
# 就條這 口水都流出來弓
I mean this one. He's drooling.
# 口水都流出來了
Yea, he's drooling.
# 等一下來啊
It'll be your turn very soon.
# 讓我吃先
But let me finish first.
# 這個(鐵皮)石斛
This shi hu,
# 這(鐵皮)石斛
this shi hu,
# 也可以吃的
is also edible.
# 嗯 好香
Um! It smells really good!
# 不過有點老 有點 糯糯的
But it's a bit old, a bit, mushy.
# 好啦 今天的視頻到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 我吃肉啦
It's my meal time now.